LinkedIn is a bit of a mess at the moment.
It feels like almost every post is AI written
with AI images. And the weird part is LinkedIn
encouraged all of it. And you can tell it's a
problem when even LinkedIn CPO said AI slop is
a top priority for all of us. Over 40% of posts
seem to be fully written by AI. But the real
problem is much much worse. Fake profiles and
fake candidates are everywhere. Some from North
Koreans who infiltrated Fortune 500 companies. How
did this happen? And how, despite all of this,
is LinkedIn making more money now than ever.
Okay, so what's actually going on over at
LinkedIn? If you want those generic AI,
it's not X, it's Y posts. They're everywhere
on LinkedIn. Then they get 100 replies saying
yes or I agree. It's honestly fascinating
to look in on or the wildest take you've
ever heard ending with agree question mark
and 100 people replying agree so funny.
Or AI summaries of the most basic insights
you've ever heard. It's not just text either.
Stock photos and real photos are being replaced
with weird uncanny AI photos or videos. And more
recently, claude generated graphics. These are
everywhere. Not as bad as some other AI images,
but once you see it, you can't really unsee it.
But how bad are things really? Over 1 million
posts of more than 50 words on LinkedIn, Reddit,
Substack, and Medium were scanned by Pangram,
an AI detection firm. 62% of all AI flag content
came from LinkedIn, even though it made up only
one-third of content scanned. But looking closer,
the numbers get even worse. More than 40% of long-
form posts and even 30% of short form were flagged
as fully AI generated, compared to 31% on medium
and just 4.4% on Reddit. Another detection firm,
Originality.ai, AI noticed a similar pattern after
it flagged 54% of 8,795 LinkedIn posts published
between January 2018 and October 2024 as likely
AI generated. The ironic part is that LinkedIn
has been encouraging and facilitating all of it.
They fill their feed with AI generated articles
that anyone can contribute to through a feature
called collaborative articles. And if you kept
up with those prompts regularly within your area
of expertise, LinkedIn had a gold top voice
badge waiting for you. In fact, with premium,
you can skip reading posts and ask AI to help you
digest the information. Why read posts when you
can just read an AI summary. Though, if the
post itself is AI, then yeah, fair enough,
I guess. Not confident with what you want to post?
There's also an enhance the post button for that,
but that might now have you flagged by LinkedIn's
AI system. But all of this is hurting real experts
while helping fake ones. Genuine professionals
can have their nonI work flagged as AI generated,
while anyone can use AI to manufacture the
appearance of expertise. This is a problem for the
internet, but especially LinkedIn. When you can't
tell who's real anymore, trust starts to collapse.
He has gotten so bad that CEOs of other platforms
like Substack are trying to avoid becoming another
LinkedIn. We're sick of SLOP and we don't want
Substack to turn into LinkedIn. So the question
is why? Why do this? Why encourage so much AI?
Surely this makes LinkedIn less usable. Well,
LinkedIn has a lot to gain from AI assisted
content. AI reduces the effort required to
write a post, motivating the average user who
is unlikely to publish anything otherwise.
It makes the feed look more active with AI
generated comments creating the illusion of
stronger networking. This makes for a good endear
report, a rise in engagement and content creation
increasing the data presented to advertisers.
Meanwhile, users complain about content fatigue.
Most of all, they are paid to continue as most
of these features are locked behind a premium.
And it seems users were buying into it. 90% of
premium users who tried LinkedIn AI reported being
satisfied. Premium revenue grew by 25% bringing in
$1.7 billion in 2023. But despite all that growth,
something wasn't adding up. LinkedIn CEO Ryan
Rosslansky called for users to sound authentic,
warning that people posting AI generated content
can get called out on the platform. Now AI content
is getting suppressed after all those promises
to enhance your posts and take on your workload.
Even the gold top voice badge was removed. It
is challenging to maintain the highest quality
standards for our community top voice badges as
they are currently awarded automatically. The
scale of this is much worse than you'd think.
Recently, Originality AI system flagged 81%
of 5,000 LinkedIn posts from July as likely AI
generated. So, why go allin on AI than backpedal?
And all while LinkedIn seems to be making more
money pushing AI, but also, you can't just ignore
these posts or ignore LinkedIn altogether, right?
Well, the real problem isn't just the posts,
but something else. And it affects all of us.
Even if you don't post or comment on LinkedIn,
the worst of it isn't sitting in your feed. It's
happening behind the scenes. Behind those views
and engagement numbers, bots, automation tools,
and coordinated activity can quietly manufacture
interactions, making posts look far more
popular than they really are. And if LinkedIn's
engagement can be manipulated without users even
realizing it, what use are the platform's numbers,
its algorithm, and ultimately its business?
LinkedIn is cracking down on generated comments
with hundreds of thousands of automated comment
attempts blocked every day. In just a few months,
billions of automation attempts have
been blocked, aka actions by a bot,
or what a script tried to perform. These can be
comments, connection requests, mass likes, DMs,
but also profile scraping. Some of these bots have
even resorted to posting the same content multiple
times, hoping that some of it can bypass detection
systems. Then there are the scam job posts. These
have existed long before AI, but now thanks to AI,
scammers are getting better at making a job post
sound more credible, making it easier for them to
attract professionals. As a result, scam job posts
are increasing. But it works both ways with fake
profiles. A bad post can be reinforced by hundreds
of automated comments, making it look more popular
than it actually is and leading to decreased trust
in professional articles. Fake job experience is
not the only thing employers have to worry about.
According to a recent Gartner study, within 3
years, one in four candidate profiles could be
fake. How can a recruiter detect a fake profile?
Well, the solution is very ironic, but more on
that later. According to the same study, 6% of
3,000 people admitted to interview fraud. With AI,
the possibilities of what could happen are
endless. In June 2025, Microsoft's threat
intelligence team identified North Korean workers
using faked LinkedIn profiles to send messages to
recruiters and land remote jobs. AI has increased
the scale of these operations, allowing them to
steal data and send it to the Democratic People's
Republic of Korea. Over time, we've observed these
fake résumés and employee documents noticeably
improving in quality, now appearing more polished
and lacking grammatical errors facilitated by
AI. But the damage has already been done. Over
300 companies, including Fortune 500 companies,
employed some of them between 2020 and 2022.
Last year, two North Korean nationals and three
facilitators generated at least $866,000 in
revenue from just 10 of at least 64 infiltrated
US companies. Even normal job applications on
LinkedIn have increased by 45% year-over-year
with 11,000 applications submitted every minute.
A Canva survey found that 45% of applicants are
already using AI to apply for jobs. It makes sense
for ordinary people to use AI in job hunting.
Use what you have available. But there is a weird
black hole on LinkedIn right now. The networking
goal is falling apart when the person posting,
replying, and applying for jobs could be AI or
posting fake graphics and fake insights to seem
like an expert. This competition makes things
much worse for the average LinkedIn user. So,
what is LinkedIn doing about it? And how, after
all this evidence, are they making more money
than ever? Well, ironically, they created the
problem and are now selling the solution to it.
If you've watched this far, consider subscribing.
It helps the channel and means you won't miss
future videos. Everything looks good on paper with
an 18% increase in time spent on the platform,
specifically on comments and 10% growth
in content consumption. I wonder if that
data point is actually on comments or if it's
just people trying to figure out if a post is
actually AI. Regardless, in their Q4 financials,
there was a 12% increase in revenue and premium
users also grew in the double digits. Marketing
solutions also grew by 16%. But one metric is
moving in the wrong direction. Video views are
going down by 36%. Creators have seen average
views fall from 2430 to 1,380 while video posting
has doubled. But how are these figures for the
most part improving? With one thing, AI. Despite
LinkedIn seeming to be scaling back on AI, its
AI powered hiring products are expanding rapidly.
The more AI generated content floods the platform,
the more valuable LinkedIn's AI tools for
professionals become. everything is polished
and so much of it looks exactly the same because
in a way it is. Then recruiters are left combing
through repetitive template-like résumés just to
find qualified candidates. Recruiters may receive
more applications but the extra volume does not
necessarily represent more qualified people.
So they pay for LinkedIn's tool to solve the
problem. In LinkedIn's own earnings highlights,
recruiters at more than 20,000 companies are using
its AI powered hiring solutions and seeds grew
by 140% quarter over quarter. Meanwhile, the AI
tools on the platform encourage users to polish
their profiles within minutes and include relevant
keywords to get discovered by recruiters. LinkedIn
says recruiters using hiring assistant save about
an hour and a half per role and review 81% fewer
profiles to find a qualified match. So, LinkedIn
created a problem first, then sold the solution.
But LinkedIn at least has realized that the
amount of slop is a bit of a problem. On June 4th,
LinkedIn announced that its systems could detect
generic and AI generated content with 94% accuracy
in early testing. It now has a seems like AI slot
button on posts, helping users flag lowquality or
AI generated content. This button went viral and
it sort of shows how bad things are if LinkedIn
has to add something like this. LinkedIn also
stepped up its bot detection with hundreds of
thousands of automated comment attempts blocked
every day. You can also use a filter to restrict
your feed to verify posts, which is nice. But
just days after this AI crackdown was announced,
Microsoft rolled out expanded co-pilot AI
writing features integrated directly into
LinkedIn's interface. And this shows the state of
the average LinkedIn post. The same day the slop
button arrived, it also removed enhancer post
three years after introducing it. Ironically,
the AI slop flooding LinkedIn is making its hiring
solutions even more valuable. AI was the fuel,
LinkedIn built the engine. But there's a problem.
If users can no longer trust what they're saying,
why would they trust the platform to connect
them with the right people, opportunities,
or employers? How long can the cycle continue?
before it breaks. To quote CEO Ryan Rosslansky,
"LinkedIn is your professional identity."
But will it stay that way? LinkedIn isn't
the only platform encouraging slop with it
backfiring. Etsy, an e-commerce platform,
has slowly turned from high-quality products
to AI scams and Alibaba drop shipping. But
there's something weird and ironic about how
it happened. Click here to learn the rest of
that story. But until then, I'm Hari
and I'll see you guys on the next one.